A Guide to the Isaiah Conley Civil War Correspondence and Research Materials, 1862-2000s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Isaiah Conley Civil War Correspondence and Research Materials, 1862-2000s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2015-051
The original letters in the collection have been digitzed and are available online.
4.2 cu. ft. 3 boxes
The Isaiah Conley Civil War Correspondence and Research Materials includes two series of primary and secondary sources. Series I: Letters, Transcripts, and Narratives, includes 98 letters written by Isaiah Conley to his wife during his service in the 101st Pennsylvania Regiment between 1861 and 1865. This series also has unpublished and published versions of Conley's escape from Confederate captivity. Series II: Research Materials contains correspondence, photocopies, articles, maps, and research files for a history of the 101st Regiment, Pennsylvania Infantry that was planned, but never completed, by a previous owner. This series dates from 1980s through the early 2000s.
Conley, Isaiah, 1830-1904; Powell, Marjorie
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Isaiah Conley Civil War Correspondence and Research Materials was purchased by Special Collections in July 2015.
Alternate Form Available
The original letters in the collection have been digitzed and are available online.
Biographical Information
Isaiah Conley (1830-1901) was born in 1830 to Allen and Margaret Ellen McGrew Conley. By 1860, he was living in Somerset County, PA, with his wife, Caroline (Carrie) (1836-1907), and their young daughter Annie. Conley was a merchant when he enlisted with Company G, 101st Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry, late in 1861. Conley, originally a Second Lieutenant, was later promoted to Captain. The regiment saw action quickly, first joining the Peninsula Campaign, participating at Yorktown, Willliamsburg, and Fair Oaks between March 1862 and March 1863, After that, the regiment moved through Virginia into North Carolina, via Suffolk. In April of 1863 the entire regiment surrendered in Plymouth, North Carolina.
Conley's regiment was taken first to Andersonville, but he, along with the other officers, were soon transferred to a prison in Macon, Alabama. In October 1864, while being moved yet again, Conley and two other officers jumped from the train transporting them, and made their way back to Union forces. Conley's account of this escape is part of the collection. Conley appears to have returned to the remains of his regiment and continued to serve until the 101st PVI mustered out in July 1986.
After the war, he returned home to his family (his second child was born around the time he enlisted) and his job as a dry goods merchant. He and Caroline had at least 7 children: Annie (Anna) (1859-1900); Harrie (b. abt 1861); Emma (b. abt 1866); Edgar (b. abt 1868); Elsie (Clara) (1870-1903); May (b. abt. 1873); and Ella (Nellie) (1876-1892). He later served as a local judge. Conley died in 1901 and was buried in Schellsburg, Bedford County, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content
The Isaiah Conley Civil War Correspondence and Research Materials includes two series of primary and secondary sources. Series I: Letters, Transcripts, and Narratives, includes 98 letters written by Isaiah Conley to his wife during his service in the 101st Pennsylvania Regiment. Letters were written primarily from Virginia, North Carolina,and South Carolina between 1861 and 1865. This series also has unpublished and published versions of Conley's escape from Confederate captivity. Series II: Research Materials contains correspondence, photocopies, articles, maps, and research files for a history of the 101st Regiment, Pennsylvania Infantry that was planned, but never completed, by a previous owner. This series dates from 1980s through the early 2000s.
Please note: The collection included 2 3.5" disks with transcripts of the letters and 11 3.5" disks with transcripts of the escape narrative. The disks with the escape narrative transcripts were migrated to CD in July 2015. The floppy disks and the CDs can be found in the accession file and are available on request.
Arrangement
Series I: Letters, Transcripts, and Narratives, includes 98 letters written by Isaiah Conley to his wife during his service in the 101st Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry. Letters were written primarily from Virginia, North Carolina,and South Carolina between 1861 and 1865. Conley's letters cover the majority of his service and contain information about the Peninsula Campaign (especially the Battle of Fair Oaks) and the Battle of Goldsboro Bridge. In addition, he writes of camp life, war hardships, picket duty, skirmishes and raids, building of fortifications, and his perspective on the South.
This series also has typescript version of Conley's escape from Confederate captivity with two fellow officers. After several months in prisons, they were being transferred to another location when they jumped from a train and made their way north. A version of this account was published in the Western Pennsylvania Historical Magazine in 1964 and a copy of the printed version is included in this series.
Materials in this series are organized by type (letters, transcripts, and narratives). Within each type, folders are in chronological order.
Series II: Research Materials contains correspondence, photocopied materials, articles, maps, and research files for a history of the 101st Regiment, Pennsylvania Infantry that was planned, but never completed, by a previous owner. This series dates from 1980s through the early 2000s.
A previous owner, Marjorie Powell, had acquired the letters and intended to write a history of Conley and the 101st Pennsylvania Volunteer Infantry. Much of the collection consist of her research files including correspondence with other researchers, files on Conley and other soldiers, general Civil War history, prison records, biographical information on other regimental staff, regimental histories/campaign histories, copies of photographs, and other accounts of the unit.
Materials in this series are in alphabetical order by folder title.
Index Terms
Persons:
Conley, Caroline
Corporate Names:
United States. Army. Pennsylvania Infantry Regiment, 101st (1861-1865).
Subjects:
Civil War; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Genre and Form Terms
Correspondence
Contents List
- Series I: Letters, Transcripts, and Narratives, 1862-1865, n.d.
  - Letters 1-10, 18 March-20 April 1862 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Letters 11-20, 24 April-29 May 1862 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Letters 21-30, 1 June-27 July 1862 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Letters 31-40, n.d. (August?)-8 October 1862 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Letters 41-50, 13 October-2 December 1862 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Letters 51-60, 23 December 1862-8 April 1863 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Letters 61-70, 28 April-30 July 1863 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Letters 71-80, 5 August-25 November 1863 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Letters 81-90, 10 January 1864-8 March 1865 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Letters 91-100, 27 March-2 July 1865 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Transcripts: Letters 1-10 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Transcripts: Letters 11-20 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Transcripts: Letters 21-30 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Transcripts: Letters 31-40 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Transcripts: Letters 41-50 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Transcripts: Letters 51-60 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Transcripts: Letters 61-70 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Transcripts: Letters 71-80 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Transcripts: Letters 81-90 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Transcripts: Letters 91-100 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Account of Isaiah Conley's Escape (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Account of Isaiah Conley's Escape ( Western Pennsylvania Historical Magazine), April 1964 (Box-folder 1-22)
- Series II: Research Materials, 1980s-2000s
  - Addresses and Contact Information (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Andersonville Prison Records (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Annual Report of the Adjutant General of the State of New York, 1897 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Autobiography of General O. O. Howard (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Battle of Fair Oaks, or Seven Pines (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Battle of Plymouth Living History Weekend, 10-12 April 1992 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Bedford and Somerset Counties (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Bertie County's Union Servicemen (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Campaigns of the Civil War, vol. VIII (Box-folder 1-31)
  - Certificate of Appointment to Isaiah Conley to the 101st Pennsylvania Infantry, 21 January 1863 (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Chapter XV (About Confederate Statistics) (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Civil War Diary Article Copies, 1955, 5 April 1957 (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Civil War Echo Bookseller List (Box-folder 1-35)
  - Civil War Equipment (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Civil War in North Carolina by John G Barrett, 1963 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Civil War Organizations (Box-folder 1-38)
  - Civil War Units, Part 3 (Box-folder 1-39)
  - Correspondence: Letters between Robin Jacobs and Others, 1993, 1997-1998, 2000, 2004 (Box-folder 1-40)
  - Correspondence: Letters from Majorie Powell, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 1-41)
  - Correspondence: Letters on Conley's Correspondence, Unknown Author (Box-folder 1-42)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Majorie Powell, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 1-43)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Debbie Miller White, 1992, 1996, 1997 (Box-folder 1-44)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Majorie Powell, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 1-45)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Majorie Powell, 1996-2000, n.d. (Box-folder 1-46)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Majorie Powell, Cards and Envelopes (Box-folder 1-47)
  - Culpepper County Chamber of Commerce (Box-folder 1-48)
  - Culpepper County Information (Box-folder 1-49)
  - Dedication of the Memorial, Andersonville, Georgia, 1905 (Box-folder 1-50)
  - Diary of S.J. Gibson, 1864 (Box-folder 1-51)
  - Disease in the Civil War, Natural Biological Warfare, 1968 (Box-folder 1-52)
  - From the Flag to the Cross; or Scenes and Incidents of Christianity in War, 1872 (Box-folder 1-53)
  - Gaston House Hotel (Box-folder 1-54)
  - Genealogy Home Page (Box-folder 1-55)
  - Georgia Civil War Information (Box-folder 1-56)
  - Harrison, History of Bedford, Somerset, and Fulton Counties (Box-folder 1-57)
  - Histories of the Several Regiments and Battalions (Box-folder 1-58)
  - History of Bedford, Somerset, and Fulton Counties (Box-folder 1-59)
  - History of Pennsylvania Volunteers (Box-folder 1-60)
  - History of the Presidental Election, 1864 (Box-folder 1-61)
  - History of Somerset County (Box-folder 1-62)
  - Information from Ellen Zyroff, the Reference Desk (Box-folder 1-63)
  - Information on Bedford County Soliders' Monument (Box-folder 1-64)
  - Kennedy Farm (Box-folder 1-65)
  - Lampher Papers (Box-folder 1-66)
  - Legal Documents (Conely's and Others) (Box-folder 1-67)
  - Library of Congress, History of Pennsylvania Volunteers (Box-folder 1-68)
  - Lineage of the Conley Family (Box-folder 1-69)
  - Letters: Copies of Letters, 1863 (Box-folder 1-70)
  - Letters: Sullivan Ballou Letter (Box-folder 1-71)
  - Magazines: Civil War Times, vol. XXXII, no. 1 and 2, March-June 1993 (Box-folder 1-72)
  - Maps: Arlington, Va (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Maps: Civil War Battlefield (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Maps: County of Culpepper, Va (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Maps: Pennsylvania Section (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Maps: National Parks (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Maps: National Parks, Gettysburg (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Maps: Sight Seeing (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Maps: State Maps (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Maps: Tarboro, NC (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Maps: Whitehall, NC (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Marshall House (Box-folder 2-11)
  - McCellan's Plantation Article from Civil War Times Illustrated, Jan-Feb 1994 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Fort Bedford Museum and Old Bedford Village (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Port O' Plymouth Roanoke River Museum (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Michigan in the War, 1880 (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Michigan Volunteers (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Military Affairs in Pennsylvania, 1861-1865 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Military Biography of the Civil War, vol. 1 (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Military Biographies (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Military History, Owen's Books (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Military History Institute (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Military Service History (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Misc. Papers (n.d.) (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Morningside Titles (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Muster Rolls, 101st and 108th Regiment (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Newsletter, Summer 1992 (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Newspaper Titles, Abbreviations, and Dates Surveyed (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Newspapers: Bedford Gazette, 1904 and 1995 (Box-folder 2-28)
  - Newspapers: Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, vol. XVI, no. 407, 18 July 1863 (Box-folder 2-29)
  - Newspaper: LSU Press, Civil War Book Sale, 1987 (Box-folder 2-30)
  - Newspaper: New York Tribune, 9 July 1863 (Box-folder 2-31)
  - Newspaper: The New York Herald (Reprint), 15 April 1865 (Box-folder 2-32)
  - North Carolina and S.E. Virginia, ch. XXX (Box-folder 2-33)
  - North Carolina Historical Review (Box-folder 2-34)
  - Notes: Genealogy (Box-folder 2-35)
  - Notes: Index Cards (Box-folder 2-36)
  - Notes (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-37 to 2-38)
  - Pennsylvania Regiments (Box-folder 2-39)
  - Painting Description of "Bring Up Your Troops, Gentlemen" (Box-folder 2-40)
  - Pamphlets: Regulation for Public Use of the National Archives and Military Service (Box-folder 2-41)
  - Pamphlets: Santos Miniatures, Mail Order Catalog (Box-folder 2-42)
  - Pamphlets: The NC Historical Review, vol. LXXII, no. 2, April 1995 (Box-folder 2-43)
  - Peninsular Campaign, Va, ch. XXIII (Box-folder 2-44)
  - Pennsylvania Historical Museum Overview (Box-folder 2-45)
  - Photos (2 folders) (Box-folder 2-46 to 2-47)
  - Photos: Copies (Box-folder 2-48)
  - Photos: Negatives (Box-folder 2-49)
  - Photocopies of Conley's Letters (Box-folder 2-50)
  - Pioneer Library (Box-folder 2-51)
  - Plymouth Pilgrims (Box-folder 2-52)
  - Plymouth Pilgrims Descendent Society (Box-folder 2-53)
  - Prisoners of War (Box-folder 2-54)
  - Records from Bedford County, 1800s (Box-folder 2-55)
  - Record Groups in the Pennsylvania Archives Guide (Box-folder 2-56)
  - Records of the County Governments (Box-folder 2-57)
  - Records of the Municipal Governments (Box-folder 2-58)
  - Regimental Histories (Box-folder 2-59)
  - Regimental Histories: 101st and 102nd (Box-folder 2-60)
  - Regimental Losses in the American Civil War (Box-folder 2-61)
  - Rifle and Light Infantry Tactics (Box-folder 2-62)
  - Schellsburg Cemetery (Box-folder 2-63)
  - State Archives of Pennsylvania Information (Box-folder 2-64)
  - Tales of Old Monroe, no. 1-8 (Box-folder 2-65)
  - Tales of Old Monroe, no. 9-15 (Box-folder 2-66)
  - The Capture of Plymouth (Box-folder 2-67)
  - The Siege and Capture of Plymouth (Box-folder 2-68)
  - Trinity Lutheran's, 175th Anniversary (Box-folder 2-69)
  - Veteran Records from the National Archives (Box-folder 2-70)
  - "Voices from Plymouth" vol.1-2, no. 1-8, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2-71)
  - "Voices from Plymouth" vol.3-4, no. 9-16, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 2-72)
  - "Voices from Plymouth" vol.5-6, no. 17-24, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2-73)
  - "Voices from Plymouth" vol.7-8, no. 25-32, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 2-74)
  - "Voices from Plymouth" vol.9-10, no. 33 and 34, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 2-75)
  - War of the Rebellion (Box-folder 2-76)
  - Web Printouts (Box-folder 2-77)
  - Web Printouts: US Civil War Center (Box-folder 2-78)
  - Western Pennsylvania Genealogy Society (Box-folder 2-79)
  - Western Pennsylvania Historical Magazine (Box-folder 2-80)
  - Yahoo! Search Information (Box-folder 2-81)
  - 2nd Regiment, North Carolina and New York (Box-folder 2-82)
  - 10th Regiment (Box-folder 2-83)
  - 24th Regiment (Box-folder 2-84)
  - 55th Regiment (Box-folder 2-85)
  - 76th Regiment (Box-folder 2-86)
  - 83rd-104th Regiment (Box-folder 2-87)
  - 85th Regiment (Box-folder 2-88)
  - 85th Regiment: History (Box-folder 2-89)
  - 85th Regiment: Muster Dates and Remarks (Box-folder 2-90)
  - 96th Regiment (Box-folder 2-91)
  - 99th-107th Pennsylvania Infantry Summaries (Box-folder 2-92)
  - 101st Regiment (Box-folder 3-1)
  - 101st Regiment: Bibliography (Box-folder 3-2)
  - 101st Regiment: Death Notice (Box-folder 3-3)
  - 101st Regiment: Further Reading, Compendium of the War of the Rebellion (Box-folder 3-4)
  - 101st Regiment: History (Box-folder 3-5)
  - 101st Regiment: History of the 101st Regiment (Box-folder 3-6)
  - 101st Regiment: Information (Box-folder 3-7)
  - 101st Regiment: Letters of Edward Nicolas Boots (Box-folder 3-8)
  - 101st Regiment: Name List of the Infantry (Box-folder 3-9)
  - 101st Regiment: Porter Boys of Co. H (Box-folder 3-10)
  - 101st Regiment: Roster (Box-folder 3-11)
  - 101st Regiment: Volunteers Mentioned in Isaiah Conley's Letters (Box-folder 3-12)
  - 103rd Regiment (Box-folder 3-13)
  - 103rd Regiment: History (Box-folder 3-14)
  - 104th Regiment (Box-folder 3-15)
  - 108th Regiment (11th Cavalry) (Box-folder 3-16)
  - 131st-138th Regiment: History (Box-folder 3-17)
  - 138th Regiment (Box-folder 3-18)
  - 138th Regiment: Three Year Service (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Notebooks, n.d. (Box-folder 3-20 to 3-26)
  - Card Files (People), n.d. (Box 3)
  - Card Files (Places, Army Units, Ships, and Misc.), n.d. (Box 3)